<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.2" packageId="edi.2253.1" xsi:schemaLocation="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0/eml.xsd https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0/eml.xsd" system="edi">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.edirepository.org/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=alewis,o=EDI,dc=edirepository,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <title>Seasonality of in-lake and meteorological data from seven lakes, including daily measurements of water temperature, chlorophyll-a, dissolved oxygen, ice cover, air temperature, and solar radiation</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Abigail</givenName>
        <givenName>S. L.</givenName>
        <surName>Lewis</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Smithsonian Environmental Research Center</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>abigail.sl.lewis@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9933-4542</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Rachel</givenName>
        <surName>Hovel</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>University of Maine-Farmington</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>rachel.hovel@maine.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3452-9485</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Benjamin</givenName>
        <givenName>M.</givenName>
        <surName>Kraemer</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Freiburg Institute for Advanced Studies, University of Freiburg, 79104, Freiburg, Germany</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>ben.m.kraemer@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3390-9005</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>David</givenName>
        <givenName>C.</givenName>
        <surName>Richardson</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>State University of New York at New Paltz</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>richardsond@newpaltz.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Arianto</givenName>
        <givenName>B.</givenName>
        <surName>Santoso</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Research Center for Limnology and Water Resources, National Research and Innovation Agency (BRIN), Bogor, Indonesia</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>arianto.budi.santoso@brin.go.id</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5437-8306</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Robert</givenName>
        <surName>Schwefel</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Leibniz Institute of Freshwater Ecology and Inland Fisheries (IGB)</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>robert.schwefel@igb-berlin.de</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Gesa</givenName>
        <givenName>A.</givenName>
        <surName>Weyhenmeyer</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Uppsala University</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>gesa.weyhenmeyer@ebc.uu.se</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Whitney</givenName>
        <givenName>M.</givenName>
        <surName>Woelmer</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>University of Waikato</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>wwoelmer@waikato.ac.nz</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5147-3877</userId>
    </creator>
    <pubDate>2026-01-23</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>This data product supports the manuscript "Seasons and seasonality in lakes: a synthesis amid global change" (Lewis et al. 2026; in review). Data were analyzed to understand how seasonality varies among diverse lakes and variables. Specifically, this data publication includes daily mean water temperature, chlorophyll-a, and dissolved oxygen at multiple depths, ice cover (binary), air temperature and solar radiation. Data availability and collection methods differ among lakes, as described in the Methods.</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>limnology</keyword>
      <keyword>water quality</keyword>
      <keyword>Lake, Reservoir, Impoundment</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Cuahsi</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>water temperature</keyword>
      <keyword>dissolved oxygen</keyword>
      <keyword>chlorophyll-a</keyword>
      <keyword>lakes</keyword>
      <keyword>seasonality</keyword>
      <keyword>air temperature</keyword>
      <keyword>solar radiation</keyword>
      <keyword>ice</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>This information is released under the Creative Commons license - Attribution - CC BY (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). The consumer of these data ("Data User" herein) is required to cite it appropriately in any publication that results from its use. The Data User should realize that these data may be actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the authors of these data if any questions about methodology or results occur. Where appropriate, the Data User is encouraged to consider collaboration or co-authorship with the authors. The Data User should realize that misinterpretation of data may occur if used out of context of the original study. While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and associated documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is." The Data User should be aware, however, that data are updated periodically and it is the responsibility of the Data User to check for new versions of the data. The data authors and the repository where these data were obtained shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of the data. Thank you.
</para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Erken</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>18.6334</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>18.6334</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>59.83917</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>59.83917</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Arendsee</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>11.47521</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>11.47521</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>52.89099</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>52.89099</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Midway Pond</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-70.54187</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-70.54187</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>44.9312095</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>44.9312095</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Rerewhakaaitu</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>176.5022</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>176.5022</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-38.2936</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-38.2936</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Mohonk Lake</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-74.157613</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-74.157613</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>41.7659849</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>41.7659849</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Tanganyika</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>29.54517622429039</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>29.54517622429039</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-6.243460677</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-6.243460677</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Batur</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>115.40702843735733</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>115.40702843735733</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-8.2587</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-8.2587</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2012-06-21</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2024-10-16</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>completed</description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Abigail</givenName>
        <givenName>S. L.</givenName>
        <surName>Lewis</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Smithsonian Environmental Research Center</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>abigail.sl.lewis@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9933-4542</userId>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>We compiled in-lake and meteorological data from seven lakes. Data include water temperature, chlorophyll-a, and dissolved oxygen at multiple depths, ice cover (binary), air temperature, and solar radiation. All data are summarized to a daily mean at each lake/depth. Data collection methods are described in detail below. </para>
          <para>Arendsee</para>
          <para>Arendsee (52.889 °N, 11.474 °E; Zmax = 49 m; Surface area = 514 ha) is a highly eutrophic lake situated in the Northern German Lowlands. The lake is undergoing a regime shift from dimictic to monomictic, with periods of inverse stratification during winter being irregular and typically very short in recent years. The average water residence time is 50–60 years. Since 2012, Arendsee has been equipped with an automatic measurement station at the deepest point of the lake. Meteorological parameters are measured in 10-minute intervals with a MeteoMS multisensor and a CMP3 pyranometer (Ecotech, Bonn, Germany). Temperature, dissolved oxygen, conductivity, pH, Turbidity, Chl-a, and Phycocyanin are monitored using an automatic profiler (YSI 6600 V2, YSI, USA) with a frequency of four measurements per day during summer. Due to limitations in the power supply, the frequency is reduced during winter to 1-2 profiles per day. In close proximity to the measurement station, a sensor chain equipped with oxygen optodes at 15 distinct depths is deployed (D-Opto Logger, ZebraTec, New Zealand, until 2023; PME Minidot, Precision Measurement Engineering, USA since 2023). Measurement intervals were 60 minutes until 2023 and 30 minutes afterwards. Data are published in the Freshwater Research and Environmental Database (Jordan &amp; Hupfer, 2018, 2020, 2025).</para>
          <para>Lake Batur</para>
          <para>Lake Batur (8.25°S, 115.40°E; Zmax = 80 m; Surface area = 1655 ha) is a eutrophic volcanic lake in Bali, Indonesia. Lake Batur is a polymictic system, typically mixed from mid-May to October, and strongly stratified in March to May. Eventual mixing is also observed in late December to March. Both hourly water temperature and meteorological data collection methods are described in Santoso et al. (2025).</para>
          <para>Lake Erken</para>
          <para>Lake Erken (59.839 °N, 18.632 °E; Zmax = 21 m; Surface area = 2400 ha) is a mesotrophic temperate lake located in east-central Sweden, approximately 70 km north of Stockholm. It is a dimictic lake that typically experiences ~120–150 days of ice cover per year. The average water retention time is approximately 7 years. Lake Erken is one of the few lakes in Northern Europe that has a long history of monitoring (since the 1940s), including both manual and high-frequency automatic measurements of lake and stream stations. The Erken monitoring programme includes measurements of physical and chemical variables as well as plankton composition (Jakobsson et al., 2025; Pierson et al., 2011). The data is openly available through the SITES Data Portal (https://data.fieldsites.se/portal/), including background information, sensor technology, analytical methods, and maps.</para>
          <para>Lake Rerewhakaaitu</para>
          <para>Lake Rerewhakaaitu (38.29 °S, 176.5 °E, Zmax = 15.8 m; Surface Area = 580 ha) is a shallow, mesotrophic lake located in the Bay of Plenty Region of Aotearoa New Zealand. Lake Rerewhakaaitu is a volcanically formed, polymictic lake. A high-frequency profiling buoy was deployed at Lake Rerewhakaaitu in February 2021, which collects water quality profiles from the surface to ~12 m eight times per day. Water temperature, dissolved oxygen, and chlorophyll-a fluorescence are measured using Aqualabo Ponsel Digisens pHEH, OptoD, and Turner Designs C7F-C, respectively. A Lufft WS700 Smart Weather meteorological station was also deployed on the profiling buoy with measurements taken every five minutes.</para>
          <para>Lake Tanganyika</para>
          <para>Lake Tanganyika (3.3 °N–8.8 °S, 29.0–31.2 °E; Zmax ≈ 1470 m; Surface area ≈ 3,290,000 ha) is a large rift lake in East Africa. Between May and October, southeast trade winds and along-lake gradients in evaporative cooling drive basin-scale circulation and generate internal waves with periods of roughly 25–30 days. These waves weaken but persist through the wet season. Measurements for this study were collected at an offshore site near Kigoma, Tanzania (4.903766 °S, 29.590183°E), approximately 1.5 km from shore, using a YSI 6600 sonde. Local water depth at this location is ~140 m, and the thermocline typically occurs between 40 and 70 m. Weather data come from a nearby land-based U30-NRC Hobo weather station (4.885983 °S, 29.620867 °E).</para>
          <para>Midway Pond</para>
          <para>Midway Pond (44.931 °N, 70.541 °W; Zmax = 9 m; Surface area = 3.35 ha) is an oligotrophic, dimictic, glacially-formed lake with no inlets or outlets, located in the northern Appalachian Mountains, Maine, USA (Nelson et al., 2021). Since November 2022, in situ sensors have been deployed on a subsurface buoy line located at the deepest point in the lake. Temperature was recorded every 15 minutes at each 1 meter depth increment, from 0.5 m above the benthos to 1 m below the surface (HOBO Tidbit temperature loggers; Onset Computer Corporation, Bourne, MA). Dissolved oxygen was measured every 30 minutes at two locations: 0.5 m above the benthos and 1 m below the surface (MiniDOT dissolved oxygen meter; Precision Measurement Engineering, Vista, CA). Chlorophyll was measured at 30-minute intervals, located 1 m below the surface (Cyclops-7F CHL sensor, Turner Designs, San Jose, CA). Mean daily air temperature was sourced at the nearest National Weather Service station (Rangely airport), located 10 km from Midway Pond.</para>
          <para>Mohonk Lake</para>
          <para>Mohonk Lake (41.766 °N, 74.158 °W; Zmax = 18.5 m; Surface area = 6.9 ha) is an oligo/mesotrophic glacial lake located in the mid Hudson Valley, NY, USA (Oleksy &amp; Richardson, 2024). Mohonk Lake is dimictic and experiences ~30 days of ice cover per year (Oleksy &amp; Richardson, 2024). From November 2016 to May 2018, high‐frequency (15‐minute) temperature data were collected using NexSens T‐Node temperature loggers at 1‐m intervals from the surface to 9 m deep. We matched those data with data from a high‐frequency (1‐hr) meteorology station &lt;5 km from Mohonk Lake (Brotzge et al., 2020). Meteorological data were linearly interpolated to 15‐minute intervals to match the lake thermal data. Both meteorological and in-lake data collection methods are described in the published data product (Mohonk Preserve et al., 2020).</para>
          <para>REFERENCES</para>
          <para>Bärenbold, F., Plüss, M., Runnalls, J., Herold, T., Bouffard, D., &amp; Schmid, M. (2025). High-frequency lake monitoring and weather station data from Lake Ägeri, Switzerland, 2022-2024. [Data set]. Retrieved from https://www.datalakes-eawag.ch/datadetail/1077 </para>
          <para>Brotzge, J. A., Wang, J., Thorncroft, C. D., Joseph, E., Bain, N., Bassill, N., et al. (2020). A Technical Overview of the New York State Mesonet Standard Network. https://doi.org/10.1175/JTECH-D-19-0220.1 </para>
          <para>Bruesewitz, D. A., Carey, C. C., Richardson, D. C., &amp; Weathers, K. C. (2015). Under-ice thermal stratification dynamics of a large, deep lake revealed by high-frequency data. Limnology and Oceanography, 60(2), 347–359. https://doi.org/10.1002/lno.10014 </para>
          <para>Carey, C. C., &amp; Breef-Pilz, A. (2023). Time series of high-frequency meteorological data at Falling Creek Reservoir, Virginia, USA 2015-2022 [Data set]. Environmental Data Initiative. https://doi.org/10.6073/PASTA/F3F97C7FDD287C29084BF52FC759A801 </para>
          <para>Carey, C. C., &amp; Breef-Pilz, A. (2024). Ice cover data for Falling Creek Reservoir and Beaverdam Reservoir, Vinton, Virginia, USA for December 2013-December 2022 [Data set]. Environmental Data Initiative. https://doi.org/10.6073/PASTA/7D6BB61D52555A4B91024AD132B479F9 </para>
          <para>Carey, C. C., Breef-Pilz, A., Bookout, B. J., McClure, R. P., &amp; Wynne, J. H. (2023). Time series of high-frequency sensor data measuring water temperature, dissolved oxygen, conductivity, specific conductance, total dissolved solids, chlorophyll a, phycocyanin, fluorescent dissolved organic matter, and turbidity at discrete depths in Beaverdam Reservoir, Virginia, USA in 2016-2022 [Data set]. Environmental Data Initiative. https://doi.org/10.6073/PASTA/4182DE376FDE52E15D493FDD9F26D0C7 </para>
          <para>Dugan, H. A., &amp; Doran, P. T. (2025). High-frequency, hourly, and daily measurements from the West Lake Bonney “Blue Box” (WLBBB), McMurdo Dry Valleys, Antarctica (1996-2024, ongoing) [Data set]. Environmental Data Initiative. https://doi.org/10.6073/PASTA/5EDE066E97B9EE23AE7ABD2E9533A92B </para>
          <para>Dugan, H. A., Doran, P. T., &amp; Fountain, A. G. (2025). High-frequency, hourly, and daily measurements from Lake Bonney Meteorological Station (BOYM), McMurdo Dry Valleys, Antarctica (1993-2025, ongoing) [Data set]. Environmental Data Initiative. https://doi.org/10.6073/PASTA/3E680FF4A17518B1F391A599552362CF </para>
          <para>Hamre, K. D., Lofton, M. E., McClure, R. P., Munger, Z. W., Doubek, J. P., Gerling, A. B., et al. (2018). In situ fluorometry reveals a persistent, perennial hypolimnetic cyanobacterial bloom in a seasonally anoxic reservoir. Freshwater Science, 37(3), 483–495. https://doi.org/10.1086/699327 </para>
          <para>Jakobsson, E., Langenheder, S., Eklöv, P., &amp; Weyhenmeyer, G. A. (2025). Effects of Changing Snow and Ice Cover Conditions on Phytoplankton Chlorophyll-a and Community Composition in a Mesotrophic Lake. Freshwater Biology, 70(3), e70012. https://doi.org/10.1111/fwb.70012 </para>
          <para>Jordan, S., &amp; Hupfer, M. (2018). Arendsee profiles multiparameter probe [Data set]. https://fred.igb-berlin.de/data/package/168. </para>
          <para>Jordan, S., &amp; Hupfer, M. (2020). Automatic measuring station at lake the deepest point of Lake Arendsee [Data set]. Freshwater Research and Environmental Database. Retrieved from https://fred.igb-berlin.de/data/package/37 </para>
          <para>Jordan, S., &amp; Hupfer, M. (2025). AR temperature-oxygen chain [Data set]. https://fred.igb-berlin.de/data/package/628: Freshwater Research and Environmental Database. </para>
          <para>LSPA, Steele, B. G., &amp; Weathers, K. C. (2022). High-Frequency Weather Data at Lake Sunapee, New Hampshire, USA, 2007-2020 [Data set]. Environmental Data Initiative. https://doi.org/10.6073/PASTA/F45E2D423B7C4B5EA52C801FE24D47D3 </para>
          <para>LSPA, Steele, B. G., &amp; Weathers, K. C. (2023). Lake Sunapee Instrumented Buoy: High Frequency Water Quality Data - 2007-2022 [Data set]. Environmental Data Initiative. https://doi.org/10.6073/PASTA/ADF295AC76F3EF9BBF0DAC45EAF7FD2D </para>
          <para>Mohonk Preserve, Belardo, C., Feldsine, N., Huth, P., Long, E. C., Napoli, M., et al. (2020). Weekly and high frequency temperature profile data and Secchi depth, Mohonk Lake, NY, USA, 1985 to 2017 [Data set]. Environmental Data Initiative. https://doi.org/10.6073/PASTA/7B67399344129AFC63CD57E99E778160 </para>
          <para>Nelson, S. J., Hovel, R. A., Daly, J., Gavin, A., Dykema, S., &amp; McDowell, W. H. (2021). Northeastern mountain ponds as sentinels of change: Current and emerging research and monitoring in the context of shifting chemistry and climate interactions. Atmospheric Environment, 264, 118694. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.atmosenv.2021.118694 </para>
          <para>Oleksy, I. A., &amp; Richardson, D. C. (2024). Shorter Ice Duration and Changing Phenology Influence Under‐Ice Lake Temperature Dynamics. Journal of Geophysical Research. Biogeosciences, 129(11), e2024JG008382. https://doi.org/10.1029/2024JG008382 </para>
          <para>Pierson, D. C., Weyhenmeyer, G. A., Arvola, L., Benson, B., Blenckner, T., Kratz, T., et al. (2011). An automated method to monitor lake ice phenology. Limnology and Oceanography: Methods, 9(2), 74–83. https://doi.org/10.4319/lom.2010.9.0074 </para>
          <para>Roberts, E. C., Priscu, J. C., Wolf, C., Lyons, W. B., &amp; Laybourn-Parry, J. (2004). The distribution of microplankton in the McMurdo Dry Valley Lakes, Antarctica: response to ecosystem legacy or present-day climatic controls? Polar Biology, 27(4), 238–249. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00300-003-0582-0 </para>
          <para>Santoso, A. B., Hamilton, D. P., Nomosatryo, S., Sunaryani, A., Rustini, H. A., Rahmadya, A., et al. (2025). Stratification and mixing dynamics in tropical polymictic Lake Batur, Indonesia. Inland Waters. Retrieved from https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/20442041.2025.2598457 </para>
          <para>Woelmer, W. M., Thomas, R. Q., Olsson, F., Steele, B. G., Weathers, K. C., &amp; Carey, C. C. (2024). Process-based forecasts of lake water temperature and dissolved oxygen outperform null models, with variability over time and depth. Ecological Informatics, 83, 102825. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoinf.2024.102825 </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>Smithsonian Climate Change Fellowship</title>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Abigail</givenName>
          <givenName>S. L.</givenName>
          <surName>Lewis</surName>
        </individualName>
        <organizationName>Smithsonian Environmental Research Center</organizationName>
        <electronicMailAddress>abigail.sl.lewis@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9933-4542</userId>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <funding>Smithsonian Institution</funding>
    </project>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>In-lake data</entityName>
      <entityDescription>In-lake sensor data</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>Lake_data_allLakes.csv</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">7318785</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">2d62144631e30ac2ed020918f0e49d5c</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Lake</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Lake name</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Arendsee</code>
                    <definition>Arendsee</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Lake Erken</code>
                    <definition>Lake Erken</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Lake Rerewhakaaitu</code>
                    <definition>Lake Rerewhakaaitu</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Midway Pond</code>
                    <definition>Midway Pond</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Mohonk Lake</code>
                    <definition>Mohonk Lake</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Lake Batur</code>
                    <definition>Lake Batur</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Lake Tanganyika</code>
                    <definition>Lake Tanganyika</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Date</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Sample date</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYYY-MM-DD</formatString>
              <dateTimeDomain/>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Depth_m</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Depth of measurement</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">100</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>WaterTemperature_C</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Water temperature</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">-0.098889495</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">27.62333333</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>no measurement</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DO_mgL</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Dissolved oxygen concentration</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>milligramsPerLiter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">-0.166666666666667</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">98.2830769233333</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>no measurement</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Chla_ugL</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Chlorophyll-a concentration</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>microgramsPerLiter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">-0.635</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">347.624096458333</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>no measurement</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Chla_RFU</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Chlorophyll-a concentration</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.581262</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">21.277227875</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>no measurement</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Ice_binary</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Ice cover classification</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>1</code>
                    <definition>Ice cover</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>0</code>
                    <definition>Open water</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>no measurement</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <numberOfRecords>125792</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>Meteorological data</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Meterological data</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>Met_all.csv</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">452390</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">3a8f3ec48238f1e64f08845bbecc451a</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Lake</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Lake name</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Arendsee</code>
                    <definition>Arendsee</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Lake Erken</code>
                    <definition>Lake Erken</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Lake Rerewhakaaitu</code>
                    <definition>Lake Rerewhakaaitu</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Lake Batur</code>
                    <definition>Lake Batur</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Lake Tanganyika</code>
                    <definition>Lake Tanganyika</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Midway Pond</code>
                    <definition>Midway Pond</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Mohonk Lake</code>
                    <definition>Mohonk Lake</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Date</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Measurement date</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYYY-MM-DD</formatString>
              <dateTimeDomain/>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>AirTemp_C</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Air temperature</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">-30.6</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">28.7765151515152</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>no measurement</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>ShortwaveRadiation_Wm2</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Shortwave radiation</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>wattPerMeterSquared</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">593.092361111111</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>no measurement</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>ShortwaveRadiationClear_Wm2</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Clear-sky shortwave radiation</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>wattPerMeterSquared</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">521.530276167565</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>no measurement</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <numberOfRecords>7591</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <emlEditor>
        <app>EMLassemblyline</app>
        <release>3.5.8</release>
      </emlEditor>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>
